<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Kbs on PMWizards Knowledge Base</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/</link><description>Recent content in Kbs on PMWizards Knowledge Base</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>(C) 2021 PMWizards.com</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Organisation Structures</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/organisation-structures/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/organisation-structures/</guid><description>There are three classes of organisation structures: functional, matrix and project-oriented.
In functional organisations, the organigram shows the departments in vertical structures with the head of each department on top. This executive is the sponsor of projects inside the department that may need resources from other departments, such as IT. The Project Manager is a member of the department and is responsible for the project but has little power. Employees working in that department do part-time work for the project but must report only to the head of the department.</description></item><item><title>Estimation Methods</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/method-estimation/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/method-estimation/</guid><description>Estimation methods for time and cost grow in complexity and detail as the Project gets better defined. We start with a rough estimation and evolve until we have an estimate for every single task of the WBS.
1. Estimation by analogy This is simples method that uses a simple proportion to have a rough estimate: Example: to build a 3-floor buidling, it took us 12 months and U$ 15 million, to build a building with 4 floors, we will need 16 months and U$ 20 million.</description></item><item><title>Objective and Key Results OKR</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/method-okr/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/method-okr/</guid><description>Objective and Key Results OKR is a technique to decompose Objectives into measurable indicators known as Key Results.
An OKR table has entries such as this example:
OKR encourages the hierarchical structuring of objectives: your boss' objectives can be decomposed into some of your objectives
You should propose your own objectives but you should not go beyond 3 or 4 objectives per quarter to keep your focus</description></item><item><title>Resource Management</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/resource-management/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/resource-management/</guid><description>Resources are assets required by the project such as: human resources (team and consultants), materials (eg. consumables), equipment (eg. cranes leasing), supplies (eg. software license).
Resource Management is the set of procedures to optimize in terms of time and cost the allocation of resources by the project.
Two ways to increase work speed and reduce project duration are Fast-Tracking and Cracking.
Techniques for schedule compression Fast-Tracking requires putting in parallel tasks that were originally considered in sequence.</description></item><item><title>Brainstorming and Brainwriting</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/method-brainstorming/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/method-brainstorming/</guid><description>Brainstorming (Osborn 1967) and Brainwriting (Rohrbach 1969), aka. the 635 method, are two techniques to capture creativity thinking.
Creativity is the ability to think and act in original and imaginative ways. Brainstorming is used when there is no experience for the specific issue at hand.
In a brainstorming session, the facilitator proposes a problem and takes notes of the solutions that participants orally expose, with no filter for coherence or feasibility.</description></item><item><title>Communication Management</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/communication-management/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/communication-management/</guid><description>Communication is not what you say but what others understand: the emitter of the message is responsible considering the medium. Only a small part of communication is conveyed by words: 60% body language, 30% tone of voice, 10% choice of words. The emitter is responsible for the message, not the receivers.
Different forms of communication are adapted to specific needs, such as:
Written communication must be used to keep track of decisions, specifications and commands.</description></item><item><title>Configuration Management</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/configuration-management/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/configuration-management/</guid><description>Configuration Management is the set of processes to keep track the changes to the configurations of the deliverables.
We usually see software versions numbered such as &amp;ldquo;1.2.46&amp;rdquo; that means: version 1, revision 2, build 46. When there is a major revision the team may decide to increase the version number, otherwise, for small changes or bug fixes, just acknowledging the new build is enough. A &amp;ldquo;build&amp;rdquo; is a new compilation that reconstructs the software into an executable file that can be distributed to users.</description></item><item><title>Conflict Resolution</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/leadership-conflict/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/leadership-conflict/</guid><description>Effective conflict resolution happens through mediation that is a structured, interactive process where an impartial third party assists disputing parties in resolving conflict through the use of specialized communication and negotiation techniques.
Stages of mediation: hear the two sides and identify expectations summarise the main areas of agreement and disagreement propose objective criteria that must be accepted by both sides facilitate a collaborative win-win solution use the objective criteria summarise and formalize the mutually accepted solution Mediation is especially effective when used at the initial phase of any disagreement, before conflict escalates in the workplace.</description></item><item><title>Decision Tree</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/decision-tree/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/decision-tree/</guid><description>A decision tree is a visual device to support decision under uncertainty. The tree opens according to the available options: each branch is weighted by a probability of occurence while the leafs are possible outcomes. The decision is taken considering the Expected Value that combines the probability with the financial exposure to reach a single figure, the impact, for each branch in the tree.
For example, in the diagram below the project manager has to decide into hiring a consultant for U$ 30K to reduce the probability of a heavy expense of U$ 100,000 from 50% to just 10%.</description></item><item><title>Emotional Intelligence</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/emotional-intelligence/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/emotional-intelligence/</guid><description>Emotional Intelligence describes the ability, capacity, skill, or self-perceived ability to identify, assess, and manage the emotions of one’s self, of others, and of groups. People who possess a high degree of emotional intelligence know themselves very well and are also able to sense the emotions of others
&amp;ldquo;If your emotional abilities aren’t in hand, if you don’t have self-awareness, if you are not able to manage your distressing emotions, if you can’t have empathy and have effective relationships, then no matter how smart you are, you are not going to get very far&amp;rdquo; (Daniel Goleman)</description></item><item><title>Evidence-Based Management EBM</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/evidence-based-management/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/evidence-based-management/</guid><description>Evidence-based management is a management technique that bases decisions on data and facts. In this context, KPIs are critical: no new process can be implemented without a clear understanding of the ways it will be measured.
Steps to manage by evidence collect data as fresh (primary source) and frequently as necessary filter outliers and spot measurement errors treat data so to transform it into information (think in terms of statistics) analyse the information looking for patterns beware of correlation-causality misperceptions: it is not because event A happens before B that A has caused B take a decision but be aware of potential biases revise the decision based on new data as frequently as necessary (set triggers and automate alarms to make it continuous)</description></item><item><title>Flow zone</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/flow-zone/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/flow-zone/</guid><description>The concept of Flow (Csikszentmihalyi 2011) is a state of mind between boredom and anxiety where you perform and feel your best.
Flow is the experience of being so engaged in a task that you lose track of time.
As a manager you can adjust the difficulty of work with tasks that are slightly harder than what the team can do comfortably to help them find their Flow.
The Flow zone is a fine line between bore-out and burn-out.</description></item><item><title>Gantt Chart</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/gantt-chart/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/gantt-chart/</guid><description>A Gantt Chart is a visual device to represent the tasks in time.
Back to Time Management.</description></item><item><title>Important or Urgent?</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/urgent-important/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/urgent-important/</guid><description>Important or Urgent? When people mix up these two dimensions of any activity it gets difficult to set priorities to work. Start by identifying these two dimenions in a new task and classify it using ABC analysis (aka as the Eisenhower matrix).
It&amp;rsquo;s up to you to decide if a task must be executed by yourself, the Project Manager, or can be delegated to a colleague from the PMO and when the task must be executed.</description></item><item><title>Motivation</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/leadership-motivation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/leadership-motivation/</guid><description>In his book Drive: The Surprising Truth About What Motivates Us. Daniel Pink states that for knowledge workers financial bonuses are not the best way to generate intrinsic motivation.
TIP: Motivation of knowledge workers is all about Autonomy, Mastery and Purpose.
Pink proposes Motivation 3.0 as a more effective way to engage creative workers:
give people the Autonomy to reach goals defined with the leader (do not micromanage them)</description></item><item><title>Non-Violent Communication NVC</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/communication-nvc/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/communication-nvc/</guid><description>Dr. Marshall Rosenberg created Non-Violent Communication as an application of Emotional Intelligence to communication. Emotional Intelligence is the capacity to understand and master our emotions.
The main idea behind NVC looks simple: first acknowledge and understand your feelings before reacting, reaction must take into account the needs that justify how you feel. It looks simple but it may be difficult to master your emotions, analyse them and plan a proper response.</description></item><item><title>Project and Product Glossary</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/glossary/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/glossary/</guid><description>Agile approach in project management focuses on iterations and adaptation such as the Scrum&amp;rsquo;s transparency-inspection-adaptation cycle. The planning is done for each iteration, that in Scrum is knwon as a sprint.
Analogous Estimating is a technique for estimating the duration or cost of an activity or project using historical data from a similar activity or project.
Baseline is an approved version of a work product that can be changed only by formal change control procedures and is used as a benchmark for comparison with actual results.</description></item><item><title>Scrum Definition of Done</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/scrum-definition-of-done/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/scrum-definition-of-done/</guid><description>The Definition of Done DoD is a formal description of the state of the Increment when it meets the quality measures required for the product.
DoDs can be expressed as checklists, for example: to deliver a new feature in the product we need to:
DoDs creates transparency by providing everyone a shared understanding of what work was completed as part of the Increment.</description></item><item><title>Six Thinking Hats</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/six-thinking-hats/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/six-thinking-hats/</guid><description>Six Thinking Hats is a creative thinking method developed by Dr. Edward de Bono. It requests participants to take different perspectives on a problem, providing an opportunity to take unexplored paths to analyse it.
The white hat is for putting up facts and figures in a neutral and objective way. Look at available information and also identify information gaps, so we can choose to fill them or just take account of them.</description></item><item><title>Success Criteria</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/success-criteria/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/success-criteria/</guid><description>The project success criteria is a set of measurable objectives to be met by the project to be considered a success. It is too naive to consider only &amp;ldquo;within budget&amp;rdquo; and/or &amp;ldquo;within schedule&amp;rdquo;. When the criteria is coarse, the failure rate goes up and we face ludicrous assertions such as &amp;ldquo;70-80% of projects fail&amp;rdquo;.
Timing is critical: The sooner the Project/Product Manager establishes what is important to evaluate efforts, the easier will be to negotiate for personnel, resources and funding.</description></item><item><title>SWOT or TOWS analysis</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/swot-analysis/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/swot-analysis/</guid><description>SWOT is an analysis tool to support strategic planning. It is an acronym for Strengths &amp;amp; Weaknesses (internal factors), Opportunities &amp;amp; Threats (organization external factors).
Threats: where are the major risks coming from? competitors? regulation? technology? cyber-security? Opportunities: what are the market movements and trends that could benefit us? Weaknesses: what are our weakest links? is our culture ready to support change? Strengths: what are our major assets? intellectual property, teams sense of ownership, skills, &amp;hellip; SWOT or TOWS ?</description></item><item><title>Time Management</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/time-management/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/time-management/</guid><description>Time management is set of procedures to plan, monitor and control time spent on project tasks and activities.
Time management planning results in the creation of the Project Schedule. To go from the WBS to the Schedule a useful device is a Network Diagram used to visualize the relationship among tasks. As some tasks must be executed before others, we call these prerequisites as predecessors.
The network diagram or PERT chart (Program Evaluation Review Technique) is a tool the project manager uses to create a graphical representation of the project work and identify: (1) total project duration and (2) the critical path.</description></item><item><title>User Story</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/user-story/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/user-story/</guid><description>A user story briefly describes how a software is used so that features can be identified. It is a device to articulate how each feature provides value to the user and serves as a conversation starter between users and developers.
The Product Backlog Items (PBIs) are usually expressed as User Stories. PBIs can also be expressed as use cases, that is how Marketing people usually talks about the applications of the product under development.</description></item><item><title>Accuracy and Precision</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/accuracy-precision/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/accuracy-precision/</guid><description>People often mix up accuracy and precision. This is a serious issue for a project manager.
Accuracy indicates how close an estimation is to the true value of a variable, while precision is about how certain you are about your estimation. There is no point in being very confident of a wrong estimate, so keep focus on the estimation accuracy: is it the best you can do?
This illustration shows the four possibilities varying both accuracy and precision:</description></item><item><title>Active listening</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/active-listening/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/active-listening/</guid><description>Active Listening is a proactive approach to communication. You have to observe the person communicating to feel if the words agree with the body language and the tone of voice. As you engage in the conversation, the other person may open up and be more forthcoming when you ask questions and show that you are paying attention. Steps in the process are: Be attentive: pay attention to verbal and non-verbal cues Ask open-ended questions, those that require people to elaborate beyond yes or no Ask probing questions to check meanings and interpretations Request clarifications Paraphrase to double-check your understanding Identify and reflect the other person’s feelings (&amp;ldquo;mirroring&amp;rdquo;) Summarise your understanding and explicit the next steps (who does what?</description></item><item><title>Agile Projects</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/approach-agile/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/approach-agile/</guid><description>Agility is an approach to project management and business (business agility) that favors a reduction in time planning towards more collaboration between those who do the work and the customers.
Agile projects are typically those where there is significant uncertainty in terms of the final products (deliverables) and/or in terms of the production methods to be used (eg. by adopting new, unproven technologies).
Working in iterations, short spans of time where a a complete cycle of work is done, waste is reduced to the minimum simply because little or no time is lost moving in the wrong direction.</description></item><item><title>Change Management</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/change-management/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/change-management/</guid><description>Change management is the set of procedures that handle all processes related to modification in the project baseline after execution is started.
Note that it only makes sense to talk about change management in the context of projects adopting the predictive approach because for agile projects change is intrinsic and continuous. Also, do not mix up change and transformation. Overview change management requires procedures to document, approve and implement the requests formalize change request (what and why) evaluate request, assess impact in the key dimensions: scope, time and cost decision by the project Steering Committee (chaired by the Sponsor) update product configuration following proper Configuration Management practices Workflow Start with the collection of the change request next to customers or users the request must be structured with a clear justification the project manager evaluates the change from different perspectives to respect the constraints set by the triangle of constraints a recommendation is made to accept or deny the change with one or more clearly defined reasons a legal expert checks that the contract allows for the change and green lights it the whole package (request, recommendation and legal approval) is submitted to the project&amp;rsquo;s steering committee (usually headed by the project sponsor) that decides to accept or deny the request if the request is denied, the project manager must inform the clients that issue the request to avoid future legal issues that may result in claims if the request is accepted, the project manager must change the baseline and make sure that the team is informed to execute the work the project manager must also update all relevant planning documents as well as the configuration (Configuration Management) of the deliverables</description></item><item><title>Cost Management</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/cost-management/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/cost-management/</guid><description>The investment is known as Capital Expenditure CAPEX, the running cost to operate the product is the Operational Expenditure OPEX, and the net operational result, revenue less expenditures, is the Profit &amp;amp; Loss (P &amp;amp; L). A project may be accepted even if the traditional indicators (eg. IRR, NPV) do not recommend it. When the company believes that in the long-run the net operational result, P&amp;amp;L, will become positive and significant.</description></item><item><title>Critical Path Method</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/critical-path-method/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/critical-path-method/</guid><description>Critical Path Method CPM is a method used to
estimate the minimum project duration and determine the critical path that must be monitored closely by the Project Manager. Suppose the tasks in a project are obtained from the WBS with their durations and dependences. The network diagram below represents the tasks in the table above:
This diagram has on the upper part of each node the task ID and its duration.</description></item><item><title>Delphi Method</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/method-delphi/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/method-delphi/</guid><description>The Delphi method (Dalkey 1969) is a technique used to collect the assessment of a group of experts without allowing them to influence each other.
Steps to perform a session Select a group of experts in a topic, people with academic background and practical experience, a broader the spectrum of expertise usually lead to better results
isolate the experts and propose them a problem that you want to solve in a given amount of time that depends on the complexity of the issue</description></item><item><title>Document: Cost Breakdown Structure</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/cost-budget/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/cost-budget/</guid><description>The Cost Breakdown Structure CBS extends the WBS, that only has estimates for the cost of labor, by adding the costs of material and resources.
The Work Breakdown Structure has a complete list of all the tasks to be performed and should be the starting point for any serious estimation effort.
As you have the tasks durations you can easily estimate the cost of labor by devising a unitary (daily or weekly) cost to each individual listed as the responsible person/entity.</description></item><item><title>Document: Product Backlog</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/product-backlog/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/product-backlog/</guid><description>The Product Backlog is a Scrum artefact that holds all required work to be completed in the next two or three sprints, either with having business value or not (eg. technical debt)
the Product Backlog is organized as an ordered list of user stories, the most important stories on top, while leaving below those with lower importance (in the middle) and finishing with the epics at the bottom.</description></item><item><title>Document: Project Canvas</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/project-canvas/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/project-canvas/</guid><description>The project canvas is a document that offers an overview of the project, no need to go into details.
The fields in this form are:
objectives (what are the project&amp;rsquo;s objectives? align with the organisation goals) scope (what must be done? list deliverables and all the supporting work) clients (who are they? internal or external users?) outcome (what are the benefits derived from the deliverables) stakeholders (list the key stakeholders) constraints (time and cost limits) risks (list the key risks, events that can hurt the project) quality requirements (think of the expectations and standards to follow) necessary resources (knowledge and material) team (who should be involved to perform the project work?</description></item><item><title>Document: Project Charter</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/project-charter/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/project-charter/</guid><description>The Project Charter is a document that summarizes the project objectives, scope, deliverables and constraints.
The initialisation phase finishes with a kick-off meeting: the stakeholders are officially informed about the project and the delegation of power to the Project Manager is formalized by signing the Project Charter.
Components project objective scope: deliverables constraints (time and cost) risks and benefits must be signed by the sponsor and the project manager</description></item><item><title>Document: Risk Register</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/risk-register/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/risk-register/</guid><description>Risks represent events that may impact negatively a project, while opportunities have a positive impact. Opportunities can be better explored in the context of Project Marketing.
The Risk Register is a table with the following data for each entry:
risk category, description, probability, exposure, impact, response and risk owner The risk category is classification of risks according to their origin, examples are:
financial risk, operational risk, design risk, market risk, business risk, etc… Additionally we can designate a risk owner who is the person responsible for monitoring the risk.</description></item><item><title>Document: Stakeholder register</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/stakeholder-register/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/stakeholder-register/</guid><description>The stakeholder register is a key project document to keep track of the stakeholders and their interests in the project and their needs for information.
Components stakeholder power, can she or he affect project success? interests in the project expectations towards the project information needs about the project development prefered communication media (written report, email, in person,&amp;hellip;) This document is a key document for stakeholder management.</description></item><item><title>Document: Work Breakdown Structure</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/work-breakdown/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/work-breakdown/</guid><description>The scope is materialized in a document, the Work Breakdown Structure WBS, that is the core document of a project because it is used to develop many other documents, such as the Cost Breakdown Structure and the Risk Register.
The WBS must list all the work required to execute the project scope.
WBS ID is a unique identifer to be used to relate each tasks in other documents Task / Sub-Task / Work Package holds a brief description of the work Responsible has the name of the person or team, company, supplier that will perform the work Best and Worst estimation of time needed to complete the work Depends of is the list of tasks that must be completed befor ethis task can be executed The WBS entries represent activities and can be done at different levels of details, from the high-level tasks, detailed into sub-tasks or very specific and very detailed work packages.</description></item><item><title>Earned Value Analysis (EVA)</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/method-eva/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/method-eva/</guid><description>Earned Value method is a concise way to report the status of a project. The observed KPIs (key performance indicators) are EV, PV and AC. The calculated KPIs are SPI and CPI.
Raw indicators Planned Value (PV) or Budgeted Cost of Work Scheduled (BCWS) is the planned effort that can be converted from any units (eg.lines of code, kilometers of the road under construction) but should be treated as a percentage of the total</description></item><item><title>Effective Meetings</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/effective-meetings/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/effective-meetings/</guid><description>Meetings are an important and frequent medium of communication. When poorly organized they can be a waste of time. When you prepare for a meeting you send a powerful message: you care for other people’s time.
Meetings can be more or less structured. Unstructured meetings, such as Brainstormings, are ideal for non-linear, creative thinking. Now we focus on structured meetings.
As participants share their point-of-view in discussions you can spot who is prepared and who just “dropped by”.</description></item><item><title>Key concepts</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/key-concepts/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/key-concepts/</guid><description>A Project is a unique, temporary, multidisciplinary and organized effort to achieve the scope under predefined conditions and constraints. A Product/Service is a collection of features and functions that provide a solution to a problem, generating value to customers. A key difference between project and product is their life cycles: a product requires a long-term commitment while a project can usually be completed quicker.
Project managers are professionals who are responsible for project success.</description></item><item><title>Leadership</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/leadership/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/leadership/</guid><description>Let&amp;rsquo;s start by distinguishing leaders from managers. In the context of a project leadership is about guiding and motivating others in their work to achieve project goals.
Managers have formal power over the team: they can direct work, hire and fire, but this power comes from their position inside the organisation, it is contextual, outside of the organisation they are powerless. Leaders retain their power even outside the organisation because they adapt to the context to communicate and influence.</description></item><item><title>Negotiation</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/leadership-negotiation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/leadership-negotiation/</guid><description>Principled-based negotiations (Fisher 2012) is a technique that has proven much more effective than the traditional position-based negotiations where the two sides bicker over a single point (price, salary, etc…).
In this negotiation paradigm, both parties consider it important to reach a mutually satisfying (win-win) solution. The key idea is to consider other dimensions than only “price” or “salary”. Consider the interests of the other party before proposing alternatives.
For a buyer, other dimensions can be guaranteed, quick access to the product or good support services.</description></item><item><title>Organisation Culture</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/organisation-culture/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/organisation-culture/</guid><description>Organization culture is a subject that not usually receives the attention it deserves. It is so important that Dr.Peter Drucker used to say that &amp;ldquo;Culture eats Strategy for breakfast&amp;rdquo;. He meant that culture is much more important than strategy to explain the success of a company.
Company boards dedicate a significant amount of time discussing strategies without a deep consideration of the cultural requirements to make these strategies work.
Dr Edgar Schein defines culture as “a pattern of shared tacit assumptions that was learned by a group as it solved its problems of external adaptation and internal integration, that has worked well enough to be considered valid and, therefore, to be taught to new members as the correct way to perceive, think, and feel in relation to those problems.</description></item><item><title>PESTEL Analysis</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/pestel-analysis/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/pestel-analysis/</guid><description>A PESTEL analysis complements SWOT/TWOS analysis by expanding it to external context by focusing on:
Political Economic Social Technological Environmental Legal issues The issues addressed must be chosen by their relevance to and potential impact on the implementation of the project.
The idea is to identify both factors and trends in each of these six domains that are relevant for the project being considered.
Consider thinking in terms of current and future scenarios, to anticipate changes, preferably by telling a story on the dynamics.</description></item><item><title>Predictive Projects</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/approach-predictive/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/approach-predictive/</guid><description>The predictive or waterfall approach to projects work best when the work to be done is well-understood and the final product is clearly defined. The waterfall metaphor is relate to the sequence of steps as presented in a gantt chart:
In civil engineering, for example, buildings are clearly defined by architects from the start and are usually produced using well-known techniques so it is possible to plan every step before construction starts with great accuracy and precision.</description></item><item><title>Procurement management</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/procurement-management/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/procurement-management/</guid><description>Procurement management is the set of procedures to acquire the resources (material, consulting, licenses, &amp;hellip; ) required for the project.
Types of procurement contract A Fixed Price contract when you transfer all the risk to your supplier.
When the scope of the work is unclear the best is to work with a Cost Plus contract, that adds a margin (say 5% to 10%) on top of the expenditures that must be reimbursed to the supplier.</description></item><item><title>Product Roadmap</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/product-roadmap/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/product-roadmap/</guid><description>The product roadmap is usually represented by a table to present the release schedule for a product showing the date when specific features will be available.
A product roadmap contains: vision and direction priorities in time: what will be done, later and in the future milestones to show the progress how they work be executed Why do we need a roadmap? A product roadmap serves many purposes:
it informs stakeholders about future versions it establishes a common ground to define priorities it provides transparence into the development of a product it helps manage customer and management expectations The existence of a roadmap allows the project owner to keep the product backlog trimmed and fit, with only the stories that will be addressed in the next 2 or 3 sprints.</description></item><item><title>Project Approaches</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/project-approach/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/project-approach/</guid><description>The project approach is determined by the type of product or project to be developed. We consider three options: predictive, agile and rolling-wave.
Choose the Predictive (or Waterfall) approach when you know what must be delivered and which technology must be used. Planning is front-loaded: the work is forecasted with great detail and accuracy. The Predictive approach takes the plans as the &amp;ldquo;Constitution&amp;rdquo; to be closely followed and minimally changed, if ever.</description></item><item><title>Project documents</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/project-documents/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/project-documents/</guid><description>Not all projects have the same documentation requirements but you should be prepared to produce and update some key documents, according to project size and complexity. These are the documents that you must be familiar with:
Business Case and Viability Analysis Project Canvas Stakeholder Register Project Charter Work Breakdown Structure or product backlog Risk Register Cost Breakdown Structure Status Reports Change Request Lessons Learned</description></item><item><title>Project life cycle</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/project-lifecycle/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/project-lifecycle/</guid><description>The project lifecycle is the sequence of phases a predictive project goes from start to completion.
In the Initiation phase, the scope is discussed and a list of deliverables are agreed between the sponsor and the project manager. The main documents are the Business Case and the Stakeholder Register. Ideally the team is built at this moment. This phase finishes with a kick-off meeting when the stakeholders are officially informed about the project and the delegation of power to the Project Manager is formalized by signing the Project Charter, a document that summarizes the project objectives, scope, deliverables and constraints.</description></item><item><title>Quality management</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/quality-management/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/quality-management/</guid><description>Project quality is the extent to which a set of inherent characteristics meet the requirements of the project. Quality can be verified against public standards (eg. Health, Safety, Security and Environment HSSE regulations) or customer requirements. Quality management is developed in steps:
Quality Planning happens during the Project Planning phase and focuses on how to ensure quality.
Quality Assurance happens during the Project Execution phase and focuses on testing quality.</description></item><item><title>Risk Management</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/risk-management/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/risk-management/</guid><description>The management of risks involves the following processes, in this order:
risk identification assessment of the probability of occurrence estimation of exposure, that is the economic cost in case of materialization of the risk definition of the proper response(s) monitoring by the owner of the risk The Risk Matrix plots the risks along two dimensions: probability of occurrence and exposure. Risks that are high in both dimensions represent high impact risks, that have to be directly monitored by the project manager (red).</description></item><item><title>Scope Management</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/scope-management/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/scope-management/</guid><description>The scope of a project is defined as “the specific focus or content of the project. It describes the outputs, outcomes and benefits and the work required to produce them. It also deals with the counterpart, describing what is not contained in or part of the project. In essence, scope defines the boundaries of the project.” (IPMA&amp;rsquo;s ICB 4)
The project scope is the result of shared understanding with the client/sponsor and must be protected from unplanned modifications.</description></item><item><title>Scrum Framework</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/agile-scrum/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/agile-scrum/</guid><description>Scrum, the most popular Agile framework, was first presented in 1995 by Jeff Sutherland and Ken Schwaber. Scrum has roles, artefacts and rituals.
Overview Scrum is a lightweight framework that helps people, teams and organizations generate value through adaptive solutions for complex problems (2020 Scrum Guide) In the 2017 Scrum Guide, Scrum is defined as a framework to develop and maintain complex products A complex product is a product (or a service) that is not clearly defined (we only have a Product Vision) and / or that must be developed with an unknown / uncertain technology.</description></item><item><title>Scrum Rituals</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/scrum-rituals/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/scrum-rituals/</guid><description>Scrum rituals, aka. meetings or events, are occasions to inspect the work, the product increment, for the Scrum Team to interact internally and with the users to show work and gather requirements
Iterations happen in Sprints that are time-boxed (limited in time) from 1 week to 1 month. All meetings exist inside the Sprint, that is a container
Sprint Planning (time-boxed to 8 hours) is an opportunity to jointly agree, developers and product owners, on the Sprint Goal</description></item><item><title>Scrum Roles</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/scrum-roles/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/scrum-roles/</guid><description>Product Owner is responsible for the product success and interface with stakeholders Scrum Master is focused on supporting and coaching the team on Scrum practices Development Team creates the product increment in a self-managed and cross-functional way no other titles in the team to avoid losing ownership all Scrum Team members share ownership for the product increment The Product Owner owns the product vision: formulates it and keeps it updated interfaces with stakeholders and writes user stories decides what goes into the product backlog defines the order of the stories on the PB (important on top) answers developers’ questions about the work to do in the Sprint The Scrum Master is as instructor, mentor, facilitator and impediment remover teaches the Scrum rules to the team and the rest of the organisation mentors team members to practice Scrum values facilitates meetings to enforce Scrum rules helps remove impediments to save team members time must be a natural servant leader or a leader who serves The Scrum Team is composed by Product Owner + Scrum Master + Developers self-organised: developers define who does what multi-disciplinary: have all skills to complete the Sprint Goal collaborative: who needs help?</description></item><item><title>Stakeholder Management</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/stakeholder-management/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/stakeholder-management/</guid><description>Stakeholders are usually the single most critical success factor of your project. Internal and external influences can make the project succeed and fail, in spite of a good planning or a large budget. Never delegate activities related to key stakeholders.
The stakeholder analysis is the background to balance the formal project success criteria and the informal stakeholder expectations.
The steps to manage stakeholders are:
Identify key stakeholders and create a project Directory with their contacts Estimate their Power to affect our success (do they have a budget we can use?</description></item><item><title>Storytelling</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/communication-storytelling/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/communication-storytelling/</guid><description>Communication through storytelling is powerful because the majority of persons can understand cause and effect with no need for abstract models (Storr 2019).
Author and screenwriter Robert McKee explains that stories fulfill a profound human need to grasp the patterns of living, not merely as an intellectual exercise, but within a very personal, emotional experience.
Storytelling is a great way to persuade people by uniting an idea with an emotion. In a story, you not only weave a lot of information into the telling but you also arouse your listener’s emotions and energy.</description></item><item><title>Strategic Planning</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/strategic-planning/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/strategic-planning/</guid><description>The organisation strategy is a high level view of how to attain the vision/targets of the organisation in the future. A goal is a high level direction aligned with the organisation&amp;rsquo;s vision and mission. The project goal is to provide value to the stakeholders (client, sponsor, users, etc&amp;hellip;). The objectives are the measurable actions taken to achieve goals. To develop a project strategy is to define the sequence of objectives to reach project goal(s).</description></item><item><title>Team Building</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/team-building/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/team-building/</guid><description>A team is a group of people sharing the same objectives. You need guidance and time to transform a group into a team going through the steps as reported here. Leadership must adapt to the team’s stage of development as documented by Tuckman (1965).
In the Forming/Warming stage the group has positive expectations and is keen to show results. Productivity is rather low, people have to learn to work together.</description></item><item><title>Transformation Management</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/transformation-management/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/transformation-management/</guid><description>Transformation projects modify the organisation while changes are modified in the project plan and is treated in Change Management.
&amp;ldquo;Change uses external influences to modify actions, but transformation modifies beliefs so actions become natural and thereby achieve the desired result.&amp;rdquo; (Palinkas 2013)
Transformation projects usually are based on the CATS (Change As Three Steps) model proposed by Kurt Lewin. The three steps are:
Unfreeze During this stage we focus on awareness of how the current situation is impacting negatively the organization.</description></item><item><title>Triangle of Constraints</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/triangle-constraints/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/triangle-constraints/</guid><description>The Triangle of Constraints or Iron Triangle is a metaphor to communicate that project scope, time and cost are related.
in the left diagram below, scope, time and cost are related because any change in one of them (eg. increase scope) require that one or two of the other dimensions be adapted failure to adapt causes imbalances that increase risks to the project or may be reflected in quality in the right diagram above, Quality and Risk are dimensions &amp;ldquo;below the water line&amp;rdquo; as they are rarely observed but should be considered: if the project is changing and nothing happens to the visible dimensions, you can expect the changes to be happening on a hidden level that involve Quality and Risk lower quality in software projects creates what is usually known as technical debt, to mean all work that will have to be done in the future when scope increases without adjustments to time and/or cost the project is said to suffer from scope creep</description></item><item><title>Viability Analysis</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/viability-analysis/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/viability-analysis/</guid><description>Viability Analysis is a study to understand if a project can bring a positive contribution to the bottom-line, generating a positive present value from a cashflow of future payments:
Project performance can be measured in terms of:
Net Present Value (NPV), Return over Investment (ROI), Internal Rate of Return (IRR) and Time to Payback (Payback) These indicators are calculated based on CAPEX (capital expenditure) but OPEX (operational expenditures) must also be considered when considering the long-term viability.</description></item><item><title>Document: Lessons Learned</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/lessons-learned/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/lessons-learned/</guid><description>The Lessons Learned document should be maintained through the entire project as a memory of the decisions made and their consequences. As a &amp;ldquo;notes do yourself&amp;rdquo; this document can be valuable to the project manager in future projects and to other managers that have to face the same kind of decision.
The main components are: name the issue briefly describe it and the decisions taken evaluate the decision and provide advice on how to improve the solution The document is updated and revised at the end to record the final learning experiences, usually associated with project mistakes.</description></item><item><title>Document: Project Business Case</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/business-case/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/business-case/</guid><description>The Business Case is a document produced to “sell” a project, to present its costs versus benefits, show the economic viability to management or to an investor.
Overview A Business Case states what is expected from the project in terms of costs and benefits, risks, revenue, functionality required, time-frame and resources required. They are usually motivated by:
Business Needs Market Opportunities Customer Pains Legal Requirements Main topics justification for the project cost versus benefits analysis: do benefits exceed risks?</description></item><item><title>Scrum Artefacts</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/scrum-artefacts/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/scrum-artefacts/</guid><description>Scrum recognizes 3 artefacts: the Product Backlog, the Sprint Backlog and the Product Increment. The other artefacts are: Product Goal, Sprint Goal, Definition of Done and Scrum Board.
Product Backlog lists all required work (with business value or not)
Sprint Backlog lists the work for the current Sprint
Product Increment aggregates all work made during sprint
Product Goal describes a future state of the product and serves as the target for the Scrum Team</description></item><item><title>SMART goals</title><link>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/smart-goals/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://knowledge.pmwizards.com/kb/smart-goals/</guid><description>SMART is an acronym for:
Specific. A generic goal is useless as you don’t know how to match it, it’s too much ambiguity. Which markets are desired? Do we know which products are considered? We need more details to do a good job. If the details are not provided, an agile approach with short research cycles would provide the necessary opportunity to align with customer expectations.
Measureable.</description></item></channel></rss>